<story-context id="docs/sprint-artifacts/4-1-get-smart-recipe-suggestions.context.xml" v="1.0">
  <metadata>
    <epicId>4</epicId>
    <storyId>1</storyId>
    <title>Get Smart Recipe Suggestions</title>
    <status>ready-for-dev</status>
    <generatedAt>2025-12-01</generatedAt>
    <generator>BMAD Story Context Workflow</generator>
    <sourceStoryPath>docs/sprint-artifacts/4-1-get-smart-recipe-suggestions.md</sourceStoryPath>
  </metadata>
  <story>
    <asA>a user</asA>
    <iWant>to receive recipe suggestions based on my current inventory</iWant>
    <soThat>I can cook with ingredients I already have, especially those nearing expiration.</soThat>
    <tasks>
        - Task: (AC: #1, #2, #3) Implement API endpoint for smart recipe suggestions (`GET /api/recipes/suggestions`).
        - Subtask: Integrate with Spoonacular API for recipe data.
        - Subtask: Implement logic to prioritize suggestions based on expiring ingredients.
        - Subtask: Ensure suggestions are 'meaningful' (&gt;=3 ingredients) and at least 3 are returned if possible.
        - Subtask (Test): Write unit test to verify that the suggestion logic correctly prioritizes expiring items.
        - Subtask (Test): Write integration test for the `GET /api/recipes/suggestions` endpoint to check for correct data structure and adherence to ACs #1 and #3.
        - Task: (AC: #4) Implement UI component for displaying recipe suggestions.
        - Subtask: Design and implement the Recipe Card component.
        - Subtask: Add "Uses expiring" tag to recipe cards.
        - Subtask: Integrate with the `/api/recipes/suggestions` endpoint.
        - Subtask (Test): Write a component test using React Testing Library to verify the "Uses expiring" tag appears when the data requires it.
        - Task: (AC: #1, #2, #3, #4, E2E) Write an end-to-end test for the smart suggestions workflow.
        - Subtask (Test): Create a test that simulates a user with expiring inventory, navigates to the suggestions page, and asserts that prioritized, meaningful suggestions are displayed correctly.
    </tasks>
  </story>
  <acceptanceCriteria>
    1.  The system generates at least 3 recipe suggestions if there are sufficient ingredients. (Source: tech-spec-epic-4.md#FR3.1-AC1)
    2.  Suggestions are prioritized based on ingredients that are nearing their expiration date. (Source: tech-spec-epic-4.md#FR3.1-AC2)
    3.  The suggestions are 'meaningful' (contain at least 3 ingredients). (Source: tech-spec-epic-4.md#FR3.1-AC3)
    4.  Each recipe card indicates if it "Uses expiring" items. (Source: tech-spec-epic-4.md#FR3.1-AC4)
  </acceptanceCriteria>
  <artifacts>
    <docs>
        <doc>
            <path>docs/sprint-artifacts/tech-spec-epic-4.md</path>
            <title>Epic Technical Specification: Personalized Suggestions & Alerts</title>
            <section>APIs and Interfaces</section>
            <snippet>Endpoint: GET /api/recipes/suggestions. Fetches recipe suggestions based on the authenticated user's inventory.</snippet>
        </doc>
        <doc>
            <path>docs/PRD.md</path>
            <title>ibe160 - Product Requirements Document</title>
            <section>FR3.1 - Get Recipe Suggestions</section>
            <snippet>The system suggests recipes based on the user's inventory. Suggestions are prioritized based on ingredients that are nearing their expiration date.</snippet>
        </doc>
        <doc>
            <path>docs/architecture.md</path>
            <title>Architecture</title>
            <section>API Pattern</section>
            <snippet>RESTful API using Next.js API Routes (Route Handlers)</snippet>
        </doc>
        <doc>
            <path>docs/epics.md</path>
            <title>Epic Breakdown</title>
            <section>Epic 4: Personalized Suggestions & Alerts</section>
            <snippet>Implements the reactive 'smart' features. This includes generating recipe suggestions based on the user's inventory, sending expiration alerts, and delivering the 'Instant Idea' button for quick, on-the-fly recipe generation.</snippet>
        </doc>
        <doc>
            <path>docs/ux-design-specification.md</path>
            <title>ibe160 UX Design Specification</title>
            <section>6.1 Component Strategy</section>
            <snippet>Recipe Card: Displays a recipe image, title, and cooking time. Now includes a prominent 'Uses expiring' tag with an icon to connect to the inventory.</snippet>
        </doc>
        <doc>
            <path>docs/product-brief-ibe160-2025-11-14.md</path>
            <title>Product Brief: Smart Food & Recipe Platform</title>
            <section>Core Vision</section>
            <snippet>Develop a mobile-responsive web application that helps users reduce food waste and discover meal inspiration by intelligently managing their kitchen inventory. Users can register food items (with expiration dates), receive alerts when items are nearing expiration, and get personalized recipe suggestions using available ingredients and dietary preferences.</snippet>
        </doc>
    </docs>
    <code>
        <artifact>
            <path>app/api/recipes/suggestions/route.ts</path>
            <kind>api-route</kind>
            <symbol>GET</symbol>
            <lines>N/A (new file)</lines>
            <reason>Primary backend logic for this story will be implemented here.</reason>
        </artifact>
        <artifact>
            <path>app/(main)/dashboard/page.tsx</path>
            <kind>ui-page</kind>
            <symbol>DashboardPage</symbol>
            <lines>N/A</lines>
            <reason>This page will display the recipe suggestions.</reason>
        </artifact>
        <artifact>
            <path>components/specific/RecipeCard.tsx</path>
            <kind>ui-component</kind>
            <symbol>RecipeCard</symbol>
            <lines>N/A (new or to be modified)</lines>
            <reason>Component to display a single recipe suggestion, will need the 'Uses expiring' tag.</reason>
        </artifact>
    </code>
    <dependencies>
        <dependency>
            <name>next</name>
            <version>16+</version>
        </dependency>
        <dependency>
            <name>@supabase/supabase-js</name>
            <version>Latest Stable</version>
        </dependency>
    </dependencies>
  </artifacts>
  <constraints>
    - API Pattern: RESTful API using Next.js API Routes (Route Handlers)
    - AI Application Integration: Spoonacular API for core recipe data
    - Performance Optimization: Next.js caching, database indexing
    - Search: PostgreSQL Full-Text Search (FTS) for efficient recipe search
  </constraints>
  <interfaces>
    <interface>
      <name>GET /api/recipes/suggestions</name>
      <kind>REST endpoint</kind>
      <signature>GET /api/recipes/suggestions</signature>
      <path>app/api/recipes/suggestions/route.ts</path>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>
  <tests>
    <standards>Multi-layered strategy including Unit Tests (`Jest`, `React Testing Library`), Integration Tests (API routes, database interactions), and End-to-End (E2E) Tests (`Playwright`, `Cypress`), focusing on user-centric scenarios.</standards>
    <locations>
      - `tests/`
    </locations>
    <ideas>
        - (Unit) Test the suggestion logic's prioritization of expiring items.
        - (Integration) Test the `GET /api/recipes/suggestions` endpoint for correct data structure.
        - (Component) Test the `RecipeCard` component to verify the "Uses expiring" tag appears correctly.
        - (E2E) Simulate a user with expiring inventory and assert that prioritized suggestions are displayed.
    </ideas>
  </tests>
</story-context>